<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Gren news</title>
<description>News from the Gren core team</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news</link>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 10:57:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<generator>elm-pages</generator>
<item>
<title>Gren 25S: Easier interop, concurrent tasks and zero-install packages</title>
<description>A new version of the Gren programming language is now available! There are no syntax changes in this release, but there are still major features to talk about. Task ports simplify interop with JavaScript. Tasks now run concurrently. Packages can now easily be committed to version control, and the compiler now let you run helper programs defined in packages.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/250721_gren_25s</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/250721_gren_25s</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 24W: Streams, static executables and the compiler as a package</title>
<description>A new version of the Gren programming language is now available. There are some changes in syntax, an option for compiling to a static executable, a rewrite of the Stream and String modules and parts of the compiler are now available in package form.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/161224_gren_24w</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/161224_gren_24w</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 0.4.5: Performance, Debugging, Web Crypto</title>
<description>New versions of the compiler and core packages are now available. You can expect better performance, improved debugging and more functionality.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/240826_gren_045</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/240826_gren_045</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Upcoming language changes</title>
<description>Every time Gren gets a bit of attention, as it recently did with the release in June, someone will notice that Gren began its life as a fork of Elm and ask me to put that in plain writing on the website or the compiler&apos;s README.md.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/240819_upcoming_language_changes</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/240819_upcoming_language_changes</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Announcing the Gren Core Team</title>
<description>Today we celebrate a significant milestone for the Gren programming language. Gren is no longer developed by a single developer, but by a core team.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/240724_announcing_core_team</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/240724_announcing_core_team</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 0.4: New foundations</title>
<description>The core packages have been updated with new functionality and quality-of-life improvements. The compiler has started its transition from Haskell to Gren. The book has seen a face lift, and Zulip has been replaced by Discord.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/240624_gren_04</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/240624_gren_04</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren-in-Gren, and other developments</title>
<description>The first few lines of a new Gren compiler are being written this week. The goal is to better support upcoming features of the language, as well as being easier to maintain and debug. The hope is also that it will be easier for the community to contribute, as the new compiler is being written in Gren itself.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/240321_gren_in_gren</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/240321_gren_in_gren</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 0.3.0: Source maps</title>
<description>JavaScript developers have always had access to a powerful debugger for finding bugs in their applications. Since Gren compiles to JavaScript, it&apos;s also possible to use the same tool for debugging Gren applications. The experience isn&apos;t great, however, as you&apos;re forced to debug the JavaScript that the compiler spits out instead of the actual code you wrote.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/230619_sourcemaps</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/230619_sourcemaps</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 0.2.1: Testing, testing</title>
<description>The original plan was to not do another release until Gren 0.3 this summer but, while this is still the goal, we&apos;ve implemented enough functionality to warrant a new release today. The theme for Gren 0.3 is &quot;Testing and Debugging&quot;, and Gren 0.2.1 delivers on the first half of this theme.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/230315_testing_testing</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/230315_testing_testing</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 0.2: Hello, NodeJS</title>
<description>Six months after the release of 0.1, a new release is here with a bunch of exciting features. This includes a built-in code formatter and basic support for creating applications that run on NodeJS.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/221212_hello_nodejs</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/221212_hello_nodejs</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Documentation as a first class citizen</title>
<description>A crucial aspect of any programming language, is how easy it is to discover and learn new functionality.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/220822_documentation_as_a_first_class_citizen</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/220822_documentation_as_a_first_class_citizen</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gren 0.1.0 is released</title>
<description>Today marks the first release of Gren, a programming language that helps you write simple and correct software.</description>
<link>https://gren-lang.org/news/220530_first_release</link>
<guid>https://gren-lang.org/news/220530_first_release</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>